Malden, Mass. First Church records, 1649-2016.
Congregational Library & Archives
Malden, Mass. First Church records, 1649-2016
RG5303
Congregational Library & Archives
22.4 Cubic Feet
(23 boxes, 3 microfilm reels, 2 flat files)
The First Church in Malden was formed with the establishment of the town of Malden in 1649 with Rev. Marmaduke Matthews as its first pastor. Some of the pastors following Matthews included Michael Wigglesworth, Peter Thacher, Joseph Emerson, Aaron Green, Alexander McClure, Joshua Wellman, Theodore Pease, and Roy Minich. A second meeting house was built in 1658 with a third following in 1729 due to changing town borders and population size, and a fourth brick meeting house being built in 1803. In 1828 the church split with the Congregationalists continuing the First Church in upper rooms before having their own building in 1832 while the Universalists formed First Parish in Malden in the brick meeting house. In 1850, a sixth building was built and lasted until it was destroyed by a gale in 1869 before being replaced with a seventh gothic style church from 1870 until a fire in 1933. In 1934, the eighth and last building was completed, and it lasted until the church's closing and demolishment in 2016 due to a lack of members and funds. From First Church, various missions and churches formed including Second South Church, First Congregational in Melrose, First Congregational in Everett, Edgeworth Mission, Maplewood Congregational, Linden Congregational, Forestdale Community Church, and Mystic Side Congregational. This collection contains records documenting the history, activities, and members of First Church including minutes, publications, Sunday school records, membership records, legal and financial records, building records, audiovisual materials, record volumes, reports, histories, and records from women's groups and church organizations.
First Church (Malden, Mass.)
Forestdale Community Church (Malden, Mass.)
Maplewood Congregational Church (Malden, Mass.)
Linden Congregational Church (Malden, Mass.)
Edgeworth Chapel (Malden, Mass.)
Second South Church (Everett, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.The library reserves the right to restrict access to identifying information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by First Church in Malden in April 2022; 2022-10.
Two microfilm reels were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by First Church in Malden in December 2015; 2015-24.
Historical Note
The First Church in Malden was gathered in 1648 from settlers in Mystic Side who wanted to separate from Charlestown and its First Church due to the distance needed to be traveled from their settlement to the church every Sunday. In 1649, the settlers were given official consent to incorporate and form both the town of Malden and the First Church in Malden. The first pastor of the church was Rev. Marmaduke Matthews whose call created tension between the church and the ruling General Court due to his ordination and theological beliefs before he left in 1652. Matthews was followed by Rev. Nathanael Upham then Rev. Michael Wigglesworth in 1655 who became known for his poetry including "The Day of Doom" in 1662 before his death in 1705. These first three ministers preached in the first meeting house before it was replaced by a new larger meeting house in 1658. The second meeting house was enlarged multiple times when the congregation grew too large for the building, including in 1702 and 1721. After Wigglesworth and when he was unavailable due to illness, various supply pastors served the church with Rev. Thomas Cheever being ordained as pastor for 1681-1686 before Rev. David Parsons became minister in 1709 until 1721. In 1721, Rev. Joseph Emerson, namesake of the Emerson School and ancestor of the famous poet, became minister and remained until his death in 1767. In 1729, due to expanding town borders and population, a third meeting house was built on a new site which was more centrally located, but this caused tension with those in South Malden (now Everett) who decided to separate in 1730 and begin services in their own building as the Second South Church in Malden in 1734. In 1792, the Second South Church rejoined with First Church with Rev. Eliakim Willis from the Second South Church becoming minister of the now united church until his death in 1801. Before Willis, Rev. Peter Thacher, known for his role in the Revolutionary War and early Massachusetts history, was ordained as minister in 1770 and remained until called to the Brattle Street Church of Boston in 1784 with Rev. Adoniram Judson following as minister of First Church in 1786 until the opposition to his theological views caused him to leave in 1791. To assist Willis, Rev. Aaron Green was called in 1795 and remained until 1827 when he left due to rising tensions between the Congregationalists and Universalists. In 1803, with the growing prosperity of the church, a fourth brick meeting house was built, but it was kept by the Universalists who formed the First Parish in Malden in 1828 after the Congregationalists spilt from the parish due to theological differences and the calling of Universalist minister Sylvanus Cobb.
After the First Church split, services were held in upper rooms with various supply ministers until Rev. Alexander Wilson McClure was ordained in 1832 as both pastor of First Church and minister of the Trinitarian Congregational Society of Malden, an ecclesiastical society organized in 1832. Also in 1832, the first women's society began under Mrs. McClure with the Female Benevolent Society, a new church building was built by the Trinitarian Congregational Society, and in 1833, the Sunday School started. In 1850, the church building was moved closer to the center of town with services beginning in 1851 and lasting until 1869 when the building was destroyed by a September gale while in the process of being expanded. McClure remained pastor until 1842 when he resigned due to ill health and was followed by Rev. Chauncey Goodrich from 1843 to 1847 before McClure recovered and returned in 1848 until 1852. After McClure, Rev. Aaron Chester Adams was pastor from 1852 to 1857 followed by Rev. Charles Edward Reed from 1858 to 1869 then Rev. Addison Pinneo Foster from 1870 to 1872. In 1870, a new church building in the Gothic style located on Pleasant Street was completed with a dedication in 1871. In 1874, Rev. Joshua Wyman Wellman became pastor and oversaw a period of growth and prosperity in the church along with various changes in church procedures until his resigning in 1883 though he continued to interact with First Church and Malden and wrote "The Ecclesiastical History of Malden" in 1890. After Wellman, Rev. Theodore Claudius Pease, known for his sermons and hymns, was installed in 1884 and saw continued growth at First Church until his resignation in 1893 with the church's prosperity and changes then continuing under Rev. Henry Hugh French from 1894 to 1914 and Rev. John Francis Dobbs from 1915 to 1925. In 1920, the Trinitarian Congregational Society was dissolved and incorporated with First Church into one entity allowing the church freedom to govern itself. In 1925, Rev. Roy Linden Minich, known for his involvement in both the congregational denomination and Malden along with his authorship, became minister and remained until 1956 when he was made the church's first Pastor Emeritus until his death in 1975. In December 1933, the Gothic church building burnt down completely along with the majority of items within it.
During the various periods of growth and change in the 1800s, many members left First Church to form other congregational churches while others started missions or Sunday schools in areas around Malden. Outside of the Second South Church, the earliest related church was the First Congregational Church in Melrose, which began in 1848. It was followed by the Winthrop Church in South Malden also in 1848 which became the First Congregational Church in Everett after merging with the South Malden Congregational Church in 1870 before closing in 2013. In 1852, a mission was started in Edgeworth as a Sunday school with Edgeworth Chapel being built in 1866 before it was sold in 1922 to the Catholic Archdiocese with the missionary work moving to the parsonage and recombining with First Church. In 1873, the Maplewood Congregational Church split off as an independent church until 1978 when it closed and rejoined with First Church. Following Maplewood, the Linden Congregational Church began in 1876 and rejoined First Church in 1969. In Forestdale, a desire for a church school led to a mission in the area and the building of Forestdale Chapel in 1892 which continued to grow as a church and Sunday school until 1933 when it became an independent church as the Forestdale Community Church. The last church to split from First Church was the Mystic Side Congregational Church in Everett in 1893 which received members from First Church in Malden, First Church in Everett, and other churches.
After the 1933 fire, the eighth and last church building was completed in 1934 on the same site with various renovations since then to accommodate modern amenities and the changing needs of the church. In 1956, Rev. Walter Bruce Lounsbury was called before suddenly dying in 1959. In 1960, a chapel was built and dedicated based on plans made by Lounsbury as part of a newly constructed education building that took the place of the old Parish House. Also in 1960, Rev. William Patterson Gray became minister until 1974 during which time the church grew in membership, programs, and outreach. In 1975, Rev. Clifford Tobin became minister but was terminated in 1977 due to tensions between the congregation and ministerial staff. In 1978, Rev. Harold Landwehr became minister until 1987 with Rev. Randall Ferrara following in 1989 until 2009 and Rev. Patrick McCorkle in 2012 until closing. In August 2014, a fire damaged the front of the building, and the building was sold in August 2015 to the Jefferson Group though services continued for a short time. Throughout the 2000s, membership and finances declined, and while the church tried to continue and revitalize in various ways, it closed and was demolished in 2016.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records documenting the history, activities, and members of the First Church in Malden, Mass. This collection contains publications from the church, annual reports, financial and legal records, property and building records, church school records, records from or about the ministers and staff, records from the various women's groups and auxiliary groups, audiovisual materials, vital statistics, and minutes and reports from various committees and organizations. The collection also contains records from related churches that branched off from First Church with the majority from the Maplewood Congregational Church in Malden, Mass. The records include minutes, reports, newsletters, service programs, flyers, pamphlets, published histories, ledgers, photographic material, glass slides, VHS, floppy disks, cassette tapes, vinyl records, CDs, video 8 tapes, blueprints and plans, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, manuals, member cards, microfilm, guest books, correspondence, record volumes, and other documents
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series, four of which have been further arranged into subseries. Series 2: Church organizations, 1830-2014 is arranged alphabetically by subseries then chronologically within the subseries while series 5: Publications, 1848-2013 and subseries 1: Women's circles, 1924-1989 of series 3: Women's guild, 1832-1989 are arranged alphabetically then chronologically. The remaining series and subseries are arranged chronologically by start date.
Series 1: Church records, 1767-2016
Subseries 1: Record volumes, 1770-1976
Subseries 2: Annual reports, 1901-2016
Subseries 3: Sunday school records, 1844-1944
Subseries 4: Ministerial and member profiles, 1767-2009
Subseries 5: Financial and legal records, 1792-1994
Subseries 6: Property records, 1833-1964
Series 2: Church organizations, 1830-2014
Subseries 1: Auxiliary groups, 1897-2009
Subseries 2: Church committee, 1889-1936
Subseries 3: Council, 1931-2014
Subseries 4: Prudential committee, 1926-1996
Subseries 5: Religious Education, 1926-2002
Subseries 6: Trinitarian Congregational Society, 1830-1920
Subseries 7: Trustees, 1930-1993
Series 3: Women's guild, 1832-1989
Subseries 1: Women's circles, 1924-1989
Series 4: Member records, 1804-2008
Series 5: Publications, 1848-2013
Series 6: Related churches, 1774-1992
Subseries 1: Maplewood Congregational Church, 1772-1981
Series 7: Audiovisual material, 1649-2001
Technical Requirements
A microfilm reader is required to access microform materials. One microfilm reader is available to the public upon request.
Various hardware is required to view the audiovisual materials in the collection.
Related Materials
The communion silver from the First Church in Malden was loaned in 1911 then gifted in 1991 to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, Mass. and can be found under accession numbers 1991.493-1991.500.
Custodial History
Some materials were deposited at the Malden Public Library in Malden, Mass. between 1888 and 1908 before being returned to the First Church in Malden at a later date. Some early record books and a history of the church were loaned to be microfilmed by the Genealogical Society of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints in 1972 with a second batch being micorfilmed through a gift of Alice C. Smith also in 1972 before the records were returned to First Church in Malden.
Content Warning
This collection includes content and language that may be upsetting or triggering. These records reflect the language and attitudes of the historical period in which they were created; many of these terms are unacceptable today. The Congregational Library & Archives works to preserve Congregational history and stories while acknowledging that sometimes that history is problematic or questionable. We do this to preserve, contextualize, and reflect on the past so that we may learn from it.
This collection contains racist images.
Church anniversaries.; Church records and registers.; Women -- Religious life.; Church membership.; Photographs.; Newsletters.; Programs; Pews and pew rights.; Church societies.; Church finance.; Sunday schools.; Scrapbooks.; First Church (Malden, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Everett, Mass.); City Mission Society (Boston Mass.); Metropolitan Boston Association.; Maplewood Congregational Church (Malden, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Melrose, Mass.); Edgeworth Chapel (Malden, Mass.); Second South Church (Everett, Mass.); Forestdale Community Church (Malden, Mass.); Linden Congregational Church (Malden, Mass.); Mystic Side Congregational Church (Everett, Mass.); First Parish (Malden, Mass.); Malden (Mass.); Matthews, Marmaduke (1606-1683); Wigglesworth, Michael (1631-1705); Emerson, Joseph (1700-1767); Thacher, Peter (1752-1802); Green, Aaron (1765-1853); M'Clure, Alexander W. (Alexander Wilson) (1808-1865); Wellman, Joshua W. (Joshua Wyman) (1821-1915); Pease, Theodore C. (Theodore Claudius) (1853-1893); Minich, Roy Linden (1889-1975)
- Church records, 1767 2016; 1767-2016
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records relating to the history and administration of the church which includes the sunday school, ministers, and members. The series contains record volumes, annual reports, financial reports, minutes, sermons, programs, ledgers, wills and deeds, by-laws, scrapbooks, newspapers, correspondence, and other documents.
  - Record volumes, 1770 1976; 1770-1976
    This subseries contains continuous record volumes with minutes, member lists, and related materials inserted into the volumes.
    - Church Records Volume 1 and Register, 1770 1833; 1770-1833 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Typed Copy of Record Volumes 1-3, 1770 1889; 1770-1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Church Records Volume 2, 1832 1853; 1832-1853 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Church Records Volume 3, 1853 1887; 1853-1887 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Copy of Church Records Volumes 4 and 5, 1887 1919; 1887-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Church Records Volume 5, 1905 1928; 1905-1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Church Records Volume 6, 1928 1941; 1928-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Church Records Volume 7, 1941 1972; 1941-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Church Records Volume 8, 1972 1976; 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 1901 2016; 1901-2016
    This subseries contains annual reports and reports from the annual meeting.
    - Annual Reports, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Annual Reports and Meetings, 1923 1930; 1923-1930 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Annual Meeting Notes, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Annual Reports, 1930 1937; 1930-1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1931 1932; 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Annual Reports, 1932 1933; 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Annual Reports, 1933 1934; 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Annual Reports, 1934 1935; 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Annual Reports, 1940 1949; 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Annual Report Summary, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Annual Reports, 1957 1965; 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Annual Reports, 1965 1970; 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Annual Reports, 1970 1975; 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Annual Reports, 1975 1980; 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Annual Reports, 1980 1985; 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Annual Reports, 1985 1990; 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Annual Reports, 1990 1995; 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1995 1999; 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Annual Reports, 1999 2005; 1999-2005 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Annual Reports, 2005 2011; 2005-2011 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Annual Reports, 2011 2016; 2011-2016 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sunday school records, 1844 1944; 1844-1944
    This subseries contains records from the sunday school, also known as the sabbath school and church school, including minutes, reports, account books, and ledgers.
    - Sabbath School Minutes and Reports, 1844 1873; 1844-1873 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Sunday School Minutes, 1857 1860; 1857-1860 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sunday School Anniversaries and Programs, 1890 1899; 1890-1899 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Church School Programs and Newsletters, 1899 1979; 1899-1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Sunday School Reports, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sunday School Attendance and Offering Ledger, 1913 1944; 1913-1944 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Sunday School's Treasurer's Book, 1914 1939; 1914-1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Sunday School Teacher's Meeting Minutes, 1915 1925; 1915-1925 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Sunday School Account Book, 1916 1923; 1916-1923 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Sunday School Deposit Book, 1916 1939; 1916-1939 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ministerial and member profiles, 1767 2009; 1767-2009
    This subseries includes records from or about the ministers, staff, and some members including reports, sermons, correspondence, programs, and newspapers.
    - Sermon on Death of Rev. Joseph Emerson, 1767 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Record Extracts about Call of Rev. Aaron Green, 1795 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - George and Ella Goodwin Metcalf, 1870 1982; 1870-1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Rev. Henry French, 1895 1928; 1895-1928 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Rev. John C. Evens Membership Transfer, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Invitation and Acceptance of Sylvester Robertson, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Rev. John Dobbs, 1915 1925; 1915-1925 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Elton Bassett Ordination, 1916 1927; 1916-1927 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - D. H. Winslow Proposal and References, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Hayden Harris, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Ecclesiastical Council Invitation, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Rev. Roy Minich, 1926 2008; 1926-2008 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Sermons, 1932 1979; 1932-1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Minich and Lounsbury Publicity, 1933 1959; 1933-1959 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Reference Corrrespondence, 1934 1945; 1934-1945 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Rev. Walter Lounsbury, 1956 1959; 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Ministry Manuals, 1966 2002; 1966-2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Arthur Reublinger, 1972 1976; 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Minister Records, 1977 1978; 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Joanne Thomson, 1980 1982; 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Maren Tirabassi, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Howard Spragg, 1982 1991; 1982-1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Rev. Randall Ferrara, 1982 2009; 1982-2009 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Pamela Seyler, 1983 1984; 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Rev. Vicki Rieth Kennedy, 1984 1998; 1984-1998 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Ministers List, 1989 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Rev. Deborah Clark, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Jane Money, 1997 2000; 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Rev. Nancy Charlene Johnson, 1997 2002; 1997-2002 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Rev. Shawn Bracebridge, 1999 2004; 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Employee Covenant, 2002 2003; 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Marie Bacchiocchi, 2002 2004; 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Rev. Rebecca Kavich, 2002 2006; 2002-2006 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Financial and legal records, 1792 1994; 1792-1994
    This subseries contains the church's financial and legal records including wills, reports, account books and ledgers, correspondence, stewardship campaigns, and other documents.
    - Legal Records, 1792 1794; 1792-1794 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Aaron Green Financial Records, 1810 1827; 1810-1827 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1810 1827; 1810-1827 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Henry Goodman Financial Records, 1811 1812; 1811-1812 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Theodore Stiles, Amos Sargeant, and Edward Wade Financial Records, 1811 1823; 1811-1823 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Nathan Nichols, 1811 1827; 1811-1827 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Thomas Emerson, 1812 1821; 1812-1821 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Issac Parker Financial Records, 1815 1819; 1815-1819 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Account Book, 1829 1866; 1829-1866 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Expense Reports, 1855 1868; 1855-1868 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Member Dues Ledger, 1906 1909; 1906-1909 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Wills and Bequests, 1913 1994; 1913-1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Canvass Correspondence, Reports, and Programs, 1914 1959; 1914-1959 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Canvass, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Visiting Day, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Cash Account Book, 1918 1925; 1918-1925 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Church Extension Minutes and Finances, 1921 1924; 1921-1924 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Treasurer's Reports and Budgets, 1922 1934; 1922-1934 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Gifts and Funds, 1929 1931; 1929-1931 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Church Funds, 1930 1932; 1930-1932 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Building Financial Records, 1934 1935; 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Endowment Funds, 1939 1949; 1939-1949 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Budget and Treasurer's Reports, 1940 1942; 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Wills and Bequests, 1943 1958; 1943-1958 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Tercentenary and Endowment Fund Correspondence, 1946 1956; 1946-1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Weekly Offering Account Book, 1952 1955; 1952-1955 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1955 1957; 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Thomas Lang Estate, 1955 1962; 1955-1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - George Gould Estate, 1955 1993; 1955-1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Barlow Estate, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Financial Reports, 1960 1967; 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Stewardship Letters, 1967 1991; 1967-1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Trust Funds Yearly Accounts, 1970 1979; 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "We are Family" Stewardship Campaign, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)